NYSUT 'Teachers United: The Rise of NYSUT.' Research Notes. 6174/012
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Chapter 1: UFT; Albert Shanker Chapter 2: 1960s Chapter 3: Jerabek Chapter 4, 5, 6: Merger, General Chapter 4, 5, 6: Merger, Articles; NY Teacher Merger Articles, 1972-1973 Chapter 4: Merger Preliminaries (Box 2)
  - NYSTA Special House of Delegates, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    photo copy (partial) p.9-23
  - NYSUT Brochure, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    Photo copy of NYSUT handbook 'to provide background information for members of the news media'
  - Teacher Rights Pamphlet n.d. (Box 2, Folder 42)
    In Defense of Teacher Rights / NYSUT
  - Hobart Speech to House of Delegates, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    Memo: To: Members, House of Delegates Local Association Presidents; From: Thomas Y. Hobart, President; Re: Merger Agreement with United Teachers of New York- 11 April 1972
  - NYSUT Convention Clips, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    photo copies of news clippings - Merged Teacher Union Pleased With Results; State Teachers' Unity Limited; Teachers Pleased After Convention; Hobart Elected 1st President of Statewide Teacher Union; State's teachers vote unity but hatchets stay; Hobart Heads Teachers Union; Merged Teachers Union Convention Said Success; New York State Teachers Convention; Buffalo man elected to head NYS United Teachers Union; Leaders of the Giant State United Teachers Union Happy Over Results
  - Delegates Handbook, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 45)
    photo copy of handbook
  - Chapter 8 Coming Apart Articles, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    Press release - NEA Terminates Merger Discussions with American Federation of Teachers; New York teacher union leader touted for seat on AFL-CIO council; Merger that could form World's largest union; AFT statement on break up of unit talks; NEA-AFT Merger talks break off; UTP News Service, Jan. 19, 1973; MFT Leaders Torpedo Merger; Complete Merger Plan: Approval of move by two L.S. units would give major impetus to Nationwide Campaign; An open letter to NEA Leaders from President Helen D. Wise; Termination of AFT-NEA Merger Talks background materials; NEA News Service II, Feb. 28, 1974; AFT Statement on Break up of Unity Talks; NEA News Service, Feb. 28, 1974; Interview with David Sellen, President, AFT & Terry Herndon, Executive Secretary, NEA; To: Dave Ford, NYSUT NYK - From: Ralph Lloyd, AFT WSH: Selden sees Teacher merger as essential to society; NEA News Service, Oct. 3, 1973; Memo: To: State Presidents and Executive Secretaries, Urban Presidents and Executive Directors, NCSEA Executive Committee, NCUEA Executive Committee, NEA Regional Managers, UniServ Directors; From: Helen D. Wise; Union Member Rolls Top 19 Million in '72; Teacher merger Threatens Schools; and more
  - NY Teacher, 1973-1977 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    photo copies of news clippings - too many to list, examples: Four More Locals Strike; Rally for Orchard Park Teachers; New York will not be Balkanized
  - Suny Battle, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    United Teachers SUNY Local Wins
  - Shanker vs. Selden, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    Letter to Elmer S. Crowley; Memo From: Fred Lambert - UTP News Service, Feb. 12, 1973; Shanker urges teacher consolidation; New Scotland Avenue, Spring Spree & Treasure Hunt
  - Neany History, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    Helping Members Create Great Public Schools for Every Child!
  - NEA n.d. (Box 2, Folder 51)
    Cortese Tice: No gimmicks, Just answers for the real issues and an effective NEA - Transcript of a discussion
  - Florida, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 52)
    Convention '74 happenings; A few questions Florida teachers might want to ask of NEA staff members working against our merger; What the Florida Merger agreement says, and what it doesn't say; Teacher Unity pays off for Teachers
  - NEA Meeting, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 53)
    photo copy - Addresses and Proceedings of the one-hundred-and-tenth Annual Meeting held at Atlantic City, New Jersey - June 24-June 30, 1972 -- volume 110
  - Disaffiliation, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    photo copies of articles - NYSUT Programs to Surpass NEA's; Dissident Teachers form another union; Teacher Group in State leaves National Education Association; Board moves to cut NEA ties; NEA Board Commends NYC Teachers, UFT; For to City: Drop dead; Focus on NEA threats no bar to busy agenda; Verbatim Transcript: NEA President at NYSUT Board; NEA scores NYSUT; NEA invites AFT to discuss merger proposal; Teachers and Unions; NEA urges bold increase in school funds
  - NYSUT Disaffiliation Files, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    What'll we do with NEA dues; NEA declares war on N.Y. Teachers; NEA staff authorized to work against NYSUT; About NEA's new affiliate in New York; Letter sent to NEA President John Ryor from Thomas Y. Hobart, Jr.; Letter sent to Alice Lachapelle, NYSUT-CWA from Terry Herndon, Executive Director of NEA
  - National Coalition of Teacher Unity, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    article - NEA unit in coalition with AFT to build merger
  - Keep the Clock Speech, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    photo copy of the speech transcript - Keep the Clock: the address of Executive Vice President Albert Shanker to the Fourth Annual Representative Assembly of the New York State United Teachers
  - NYSTA Legislative Program, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    The Legislative Program was approved by the New York State United Teachers Board of Directors at its meeting of November 2-3, 1973
  - Political General, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    Teachers no Lions in political arena
  - Prof. Staff. Ass., 2005 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    pamphlet - PSA-Professional Staff Association: the Union behind the Union
  - Committee of 100, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    two folders of information for the Committee of 100 Lobby Day
  - Representative Assembly, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 62)
    RA Reporter issues - April 7, 2005; 2005 NYSUT RA; 4/8/2005; 2005 Convention Program & Awards Book; Report of the Resolutions Committees; New Delegate Handbook (2 copies)
  - NYSUT News Releases, 2002 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    New York Teacher issues - vol. XLVI, No. 11; vol. XLV, no. 7; Gregory G. Miller defibrillator fund; Statement by NYSUT on passage of school defibrillator legislation; Defibrillator saves a life as law takes effect; Saving lives, the union way; NYSUT makes heart-felt case for defibrillator bill to become law; A heartfelt gift; One teacher's goal: in every school, a device to save lives; A young life saved by a school defibrillator; Sudden collapse, amazing rescue
  - NYC Bailout, 1971-1985 (Box 2, Folder 64)
    photo copies of articles -- Mr. Ford bends, Cary's aid plan gets over the top; Teachers save NYC; United Teachers Weighing disaffiliation with NEA; Cutback here saps morale; future bleak; Crippling cuts sap morale here; Ten years after the crisis perspectives on New York City's fiscal recovery; Polishing the Big Apple: the role of the Independent Monitors in New York City's fiscal recovery; Statement of Albert Shanker, President of the United Federation of Teachers before the Assembly Education Committee to evaluate the impact of the fiscal crisis upon quality education; Shanker calls for special legislative session; Shanker explains New York actions, predicts more cuts; Where we stand by Albert Shanker (several articles)
- Chapter 6: Merger, Concord Convention; Merger 1972 Chapter 7-8: National Merger, Coming Apart Chapter 9: Politics, General, D'Amato Chapter 10: Educational Reform: NYSUT and General Chapter 11: International Solidarity (Box 3)
  - Paraprofessional Articles in United Teacher, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    photo copies of articles from The United Teacher
  - Velma Hill-Paraprofessional Interview, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    United Federation of Teachers Oral History Collection Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives New York University
  - Teacher's Pensions, 1970-1973 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    articles - At Last - Teacher Coalition; The Truth About Teacher Pensions; Correspondence; New Pension Improvements Won for New York State's Teachers
  - Staff from Alan Lubin, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Report of the NYSUT task force on initiative and referendum; 2004 Presidential Benchmark Polling by the NYSUT Polling Center; 2001 Final Legislative Report; 2002 Final Legislative Report; Legislative Update issues - vol.7, #2-6; vol.8, #1-3
  - Pictures-Alan Lubin n.d. (Box 3, Folder 5)
    photo copied pictures
  - Bella Abzug, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    NY Times article - Shanker Assails Mrs. Abzug; She Denies his 'Scab' charge
  - Convention-PAC Social Security, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Literature and advertisements
  - New Delegate Orientation, 2004-2005 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Constitution and bylaws, effective march 2004; New Delegate Handbook (2005)
  - AFT-Civil Rights, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Teachers, unions and the fight for Civil Rights (photo copy)
  - D'Amato Background, 2002 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Torch gets burned, but what about Al?
  - Summary-D'Amato, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    print outs of articles from the web - New York's Politics of the future not a pretty picture; A Wizard Casts His Spell; Democrats endorse Schumer for Senate; D'Amato would lose seat, poll says; It's 'dj vu all over again' for Dems; Senate candidates on the offensive during first debate; Schumer cuts Ferraro lead in Senate race; D'Amato and Schumer Tout flag, jobs; 47% in state poll oppose D'Amato; Ferraro loses lead, now in dead heat with Schumer in Senate primary, poll says; many more articles
  - Schumer Victory Primary, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Schumer wins the right to challenge D'Amato
  - D'Amato General, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    printouts from web articles - Schumer unveils new attack ad; And the senator who turns up the political thermostat; Remarks at a fundraising luncheon for Senator Alfonse M. D'Amato in New York, NY; D'Amato tunes up for re-election campaign by unveiling 'fighter for the little guy' image
  - D'Amato's Voting Record Alan Lubin's File, 1995 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Alfonse D'Amato on the record on public education and labor; Senator Al D'Amato: Research book - vol. 1 -- Voting Record, 1981-1987
  - Summary of D'Amato Campaign n.d. (Box 3, Folder 15)
    one sheet with information on it about D'Amato's campaign
  - D'Amato Lubin File, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    articles - Tell Senator Al D'Amato to stop trashing teachers and start supporting our schools; Teachers' unions will attack D'Amato education record; News fromMichael J. Bragman, Majority Leader; McCarthyism for the 1990s targets teachers; NEA/NY urges Senator D'Amato and school boards to: Put children and education first, not politics as usual; AFT, NEA tackle key issues through Joint Policy Council; Memo to Ray Skuse - from: John Costello; Statewide brochure distribution- November 20, 1997; Several memos regarding D'Amato's campaign; Several articles from the New York Teacher; Alfonse D'Amato on the record on public education and labor
  - Schumer Background, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    Candidates set education goals; N.Y. Assembly, 1975-81; Schumer launches campaign against D'Amato; Schumer calls for incentives for teachers; Schumer may challenge Pataki or D'Amato in '98; Schumer's big challenge; Schumer enters race for Senate saying he can unseat D'Amato; Schumer enters the race to unseat D'Amato; Upbeat Schumer battles poor polls, low turnouts and his image; Schumer battles polls, low turnouts and his image; Schumer or later; Some fresh (and unusual) faces in '98
  - Education Articles-NY Times, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Teachers' unions will attack D'Amato's education record; Clinton budget received well in the region; Schumer opens Senate race by claiming centrist position; Schumer enters race for Senate saying he can unseat D'Amato; Teachers cheer as Democratic candidates denounce D'Amato; D'Amato stirs State GOP and borrows some themes; Green lashes out at Schumer and Ferraro; Who? The Democrat for What?; Barrage of similar ads blurs Democratic Candidates; Teachers Cheer as Democratic Candidates denounce D'Amato; Better schools is battle cry for Fall elections; The Upstate-Downstate game; D'Amato and Schumer intensify clash over crime issue; many more photo copies of news clippings
  - Schumer Victory-General, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    photo copies of articles - New Hope for two; Visiting places with barely enough Democrats to field a baseball team; End of the road for Sen Pothole; Schumer puts big dent in state GOP machine built by D'Amato; Editorials from other newspapers; Pataki, D'Amato vacation together; D'Amato's attack style ended up hurting him far more than Schumer; Schumer sworn in by Gore again; The Moderate Republic; Democrats score upset against GOP Sen. Alfonso D'Amato; Al D'Amato's 20 minute GAP
  - D'Amato-Schumer Election, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Fighting dirty; D'Amato far ahead of Schumer in campaign cash if not in polls; D'Amato makes brief stop in Buffalo, blasts Schumer's record; D'Amato continues ad blitz against Schumer; First Lady attacks D'Amato's record blasts him as a 'Jesse Helms Clone'; Democrats to air D'Amato ads in bid to expose divisive ploy; D'Amato, Schumer race is a dead heat in latest poll; Schumer and D'Amato: what they're saying; D'Amato, Schumer wage bitter and war; Schumer mounts attack on D'Amato truthfulness; D'Amato ad plays to anti-NY city sentiment while Schumer airs spot on boyhood home; D'Amato's mother stumps falls' Italian Community; Political bloodbath to enjoy; Schumer assails D'Amato for using Yiddish 'slur'; many more photo copies of Schumer- D'Amato related articles
  - D'Amato - Schumer Election, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    photo copies of online and news paper clippings - Schumer tries to win over skeptical upstaters; New York Teacher articles; Randi's big gamble; Teachers cheer as Democratic Candidates denounce D'Amato; Sworn in as Senator, Schumer promises money for New York; several articles about Schumer being sworn in; For Schumer, a shift in style as a Senator; articles about Ferraro run for office and her loss; articles on Clinton's involvement in the Schumer-D'Amato race; many article's on D'Amato's race; too many articles to list individually
  - The Troubled Crusade-Diane Ravitch n.d. (Box 3, Folder 22)
    photo copies of some pages from 'The Troubled Crusade: American Education, 1945-1980'
  - Ravitch on Book, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Ravitch: Contemporary School IIIs trace roots to progressive movement by Lynn Olson
  - Shanker Column About Ed. Reform, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    photo copies of many articles Albert Shanker wrote for his column 'Where We Stand' -- Double Standard in Teacher Selection; Teacher Licensing Examinations:
  - Shanker on School Reform, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 25)
    Bad faith sabotages school reform; A historic document [by] Diane Ravitch
  - Darlins-Hammond, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 26)
    Mentoring reconsidered; Keeping good teachers; Teacher learning that supports student learning; The quiet revolution: rethinking teacher development; Refraining the school reform agenda; developing capacity for school transformation; What matters most: a competent teacher for every child
  - No Child Left Behind, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    NEA files 'No child left behind' lawsuit; AFT follows separate path in changing law; AFT follows separate path in changing law
  - Shanker on Standards, 1997 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    Teachers' union leaders oppose push to testing at the expense of curriculum; Always setting the standard; Class size revisited; Where we stand: 800 words of weekly wisdom; A Landmark revisited; Albert Shanker's Legacy Education Next - Richard D. Kahlenberg; An insider's view of 'A Nation at Risk' and why it still matters; Excellence report a rebuff to Reagan; Collective bargaining: laying the foundation
  - Shanker on Professionalism, 1996 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    photo copies of Shanker's Where We Stand articles - Talking to a teacher; Teachers doubles as celebrity; Changes needed in role of principal; Teachers inhabit a MAD, mad world; Is it loss of teacher authority?; Time to treat teaching as Profession; Teachers' colleagues #1 resource; Working together; Truths about teaching; The question of power; The case for national standards; A better use of human resources; Teaching know-how needs promotion; Teachers have leadership role; Turning point for American education; 4 'Key' school change; Rochester shows the wav; History making: a union tradition
  - Chancellor's Schools, 1999-2002 (Box 3, Folder 30)
    Using well-qualified teachers well; UFT school charters new course; Failing schools challenge accountability goals; Number of low-performing schools drops; Klein's big ticket item: a new system of Professional development; Shakeup in NYC puts troubled schools on the hot seat; Number of low-performing schools drops
  - NYSUT Education, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    NYSUT - Education and Learning Trust - Fall 2003 Course Catalog
  - Teacher Centers, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 32)
    issue of Core Connection- Summer 2005; folder with information sheets from NYS Teachers Centers; Teacher Centers and Need Assessment; How successful are the centers?; Teacher centers: will they 'sell?'; The Teacher Center: a major educational advance; Teacher Centers are becoming a new; Professional development: do it yourself; Local Leaders' Guide: to research & educational issues; Information Bulletin - Teachers Centers
  - CBTE Mailgram from Hobart, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    Memo to NYSUT Local Presidents and Board of Directors -- from President Tom Hobart -- subject CBTE Programs
  - Competency Based Education, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 34)
    Courtesy of the NYSUT Division of Research and Educational Services; Is performance- based teacher education (PBTE) inevitable?; The Governance of teacher education, part 1; The following position and guidelines were adopted by the NYSUT Board of Directors in January, 1974; Local Presidents' guide; Education beyond high school: the Regents Tentative Statewide Plan for the Development of Post-Secondary Education, 1972; Recommendations of the Commissioner's task force on teacher education and certification; Teacher Education in New York State: Relevant issues; Teacher Education in New York State; A Review of New York State competency-based Teacher Education trial projects
  - Research and Educational Services, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    Local Leaders' Guide: Research and Educational Services
  - National Board, 1983-2004 (Box 3, Folder 36)
    New NYS Teacher Certification Regulations - Take effect February 2, 2004; Information Bulletin: Teacher Certification in New York State; Supervisors' Rigidity Angers Teachers; Information bulletin: National Board Certification
  - Mentoring NYSUT Files, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 37)
    articles from New York Teacher; Where New Teachers find old hands who help them cope; Rochester schools in crisis; Why beginning teachers fail; Lessons; Martha meets her mentor; What are the concerns and questions of mentors of beginning teachers?; Learning from the experienced; Mentors and protgs: a critical review of the literature; Mentoring beginning teachers; Mentor, peer intervention and teacher evaluation programs; New teachers abandon field at high rate; Teacher mentoring: a critical review; Mentoring helps new teachers; Mentorship: new roles for mature and especially capable teachers; Mentor results mixed; Mentoring among teachers: a review of the literature
  - Mentors, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 38)
    New York Teacher issue - February 17, 2005
  - The Role of Unions in Educational Programs, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 39)
    Information Bulletin - The Role of the Union in Educational Programs
  - A Blueprint for Ed. Reform, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    The New York Report: A blueprint for learning and teaching
  - Charter Schools, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    Convention plots new course: a charter for change; Questions and answers on New York's Charter School Legislation - March 3, 1999; Appellate court upholds stay on education funding, speeds process; Statement by New York State United Teachers on Passage of School Defibrillator Legislation
  - Charter School Analysis, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    Not so fast: the unmet challenges for charter schools and those who oversee them
  - NYSTA Lobbying, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    photo copied pictures of teachers leaving for a lobby day
  - Teacher Unity-Year 1, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 44)
    Teacher unity - year one: a report to the delegates 1974
  - Chapter 9 Politics, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 45)
    Carey wins endorsement of AFL-CIO by 90%; Chapter 8: the Power of Unity
  - Mary Muldoon, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 46)
    History of the Mary Muldoon fund
  - SRP Timeline, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 47)
    SRP timeline: a history of organized achievement
  - UUP, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 48)
    Getting smarter all the time: the Freshman class; Voice issue-Nov. 2003; SRP timeline: a history of organized achievement
  - COLA, 2000 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    COLA now! - Uft retirees join throng in Albany to send message; Deal reached on cost-of-living increase for pensioners; Governor boosts pensions, mends fences
  - Polling, 2000-2004 (Box 3, Folder 50)
    Benchmark Polling Group folder; NYSUT Polling Center folder
  - May 3 Rally, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 51)
    Thousands rally for education funding; Educators go public at Empire State Plaza rally; NYSUT aims for lasting message; March for Public Education
  - D'Amato Attach on Teacher, 1998 (Box 3, Folder 52)
    Why fear the State Teachers' union?; The New York Observer; With no challengers handy, D'Amato steps up attack on Teachers; Teachers face tenure foes; D'Amato seizes education as hot button issue in race; Who is Al D'Amato; Giuliani steals a page from D'Amato's campaign; We need to encourage teachers
  - NYSUT Letter Writing Campaign, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    Media Relations and Communications; Correspondence; Alfonse D'Amato letter writing campaign
  - March, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    May 3 -- NYSUT Leader vol. 21, no.18; Special supplement to the Legislative Gazette - May 12, 2003
  - Member Benefits, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    Summary of programs and services; Group plans & services portfolio; Life insurance is not for you, it's not for your family; The Flexible benefit plan; Accidental death and dismemberment insurance; Everyone should have a plan; Designed to pay in excess of your basic coverage; Assist America; many more pamphlets outlining the benefits NYSUT members have available
  - AFT's Role in International Affairs, 1997-2003 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    Fighting for freedom around the world; The AFT & Labor's role in 21st Century International Affairs; Session II: Challenges to Democracy I; Session III: Challenges to Democracy II; Session IV: Democratic forces, unions and education
  - Labor Religion Coalition, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    Justicing - August 2005 issue; AFL-CIO's Dark Past (5)
  - Poland, 1989-2005 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    articles: NYSUT, AFT proud of strong ties to Lech Walesa and Solidarity; Welcome Lech Walesa!; A special message from Lech Walesa; President's position not tough enough; Solidarnosc through history; Where is the 'Strong' President we elected?; Al Shanker and International affairs; A special message from Lech Walesa; From his high pedestal, Walesa has a great fall
  - The Role of Union in Education Reform, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 59)
    Audio
  - Role of Union in Education Reform - 2005 - Supporting Materials (Box 3, Folder 60)
    2005 Local Presidents' Conference: The Role of the Union in Educational Reform - Supporting Materials
  - Committee of 100 (Box 3, Folder 61)
    two folders of information sheets - Committee of 100; NYSUT New York State United Teachers
- Research & Educational Services: Resource Guide (April 2005) -- pulled from box 3/ff60 (Box 4)
  - Research & Educational Services: Research Guide (April 2005) (Box 4, Folder 1)